<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>New directions of experience to the Commons complaint by the incouragement of the Kings most excellent Maiesty, as may appeare, for the planting of timber and fire-wood. With a neere estimation what millions of acres the kingdome doth containe; what acres is waste ground, whereon little profit for this purpose will arise. :  What millions hath bin woods, and bushy grounds, what acres are woods, and in how many acres so much timber will be contained, as will maintaine the kingdome for all vses for euer. : And how as great store of fire-wood may be raised, as may plentifully maintaine the kingdome for all purposes, without losse of ground; so as within thirty yeares all spring-woods may be conuerted to tillage and pasture. / Inuented by Arthur Standish.</title>
            <author>Standish, Arthur, fl. 1611-1613.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23204.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S95384</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">68223023</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 68223023</idno>
            <idno type="VID">183843</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08132)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 183843)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2202:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>New directions of experience to the Commons complaint by the incouragement of the Kings most excellent Maiesty, as may appeare, for the planting of timber and fire-wood. With a neere estimation what millions of acres the kingdome doth containe; what acres is waste ground, whereon little profit for this purpose will arise. :  What millions hath bin woods, and bushy grounds, what acres are woods, and in how many acres so much timber will be contained, as will maintaine the kingdome for all vses for euer. : And how as great store of fire-wood may be raised, as may plentifully maintaine the kingdome for all purposes, without losse of ground; so as within thirty yeares all spring-woods may be conuerted to tillage and pasture. / Inuented by Arthur Standish.</title>
                  <author>Standish, Arthur, fl. 1611-1613.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p. : coat of arms.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>N. Okes],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini. MDCXIII. [1613].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Royal arms (p. [3]), head-pieces, tail-pieces, initials.</note>
                  <note>Publisher suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D² E⁴ F².</note>
                  <note>Includes 'A second direction, for the present encreasing of firewood, agreeable to the nature of this age, 1613. February 1.' -- p. 25-36.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fuelwood crops --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Tree crops --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Reforestation --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Forests and forestry --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:183843:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183843:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>NEW DIRECTIONS OF EXPERIENCE TO THE COMMONS COMPLAINT BY THE IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement of the Kings moſt excellent Maieſty, as may appeare, for the plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Timber and Fire-wood. WITH A NEERE ESTIMATION what millions of Acres the kingdome doth containe; what Acres is waſte ground, whereon little profit for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe will ariſe. WHAT MILLIONS HATH BIN Woods, and Buſhy grounds, what Acres are Woods, and in how many Acres ſo much Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber will be contained, as will maintaine the Kingdome for all vſes for euer. AND HOW AS GREAT STORE OF Fire-wood may be raiſed, as may plentifully maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Kingdome for all purpoſes, without loſſe of ground; ſo as within thirty yeares all Spring-woods may be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Tillage and Paſture.</p>
            <p>Inuented by Arthur Standiſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Domini.</hi> MDCXIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:183843:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:183843:2"/>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>royal coat of arms</figDesc>
                     <head>I R</head>
                     <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <opener>
               <signed>By the King.</signed>
               <salute>To all Noblemen, Gentlemen, and other our louing Subiects, to whom it may appertaine.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEREAS <hi>Arthur Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh</hi> (Gentleman) hath taken much paines, and bene at great charges in compoſing and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing in a book, ſome proiects for the increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Woods, the decay whereof in this Realme is vniuerſally complained of: And
<pb facs="tcp:183843:3"/> therefore We would be glad that any inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might further the reſtoring thereof: We haue therefore beene pleaſed to giue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance to this Booke, and to the Printing thereof. And if the ſame ſhall be willingly receiued of the Gentlemen, and others of ability, who haue grounds fitting for his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, it ſhall much content Vs, doubting not, but that ſuch as ſhall thinke good to make vſe of the Booke, will deale worthily with him for his paines. And We are alſo pleaſed for the better encouragement of the ſaid <hi>Standiſh,</hi> hereby to declare, that Our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is, that no Perſon or Perſons whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, ſhall Print any of the ſaid Bookes, but for and to the vſe of the ſaid <hi>Standiſh,</hi> and none others.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen vnder our Signet at <hi>Andeuer,</hi> 
                  <date>the firſt day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in the ninth yeare of our raigne of <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and of <hi>Scotland</hi> the fiue and fortieth.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <closer>God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:183843:3"/>
            <div type="directions">
               <head>New Directions for the planting of Wood, by Arthur Standiſh.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEREAS It pleaſed the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie, forth of his Princely reſpect, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter repairing of the ruine of this Kingdome, for the good of euery particular perſon: the publique good of the Common-wealth, and the preſeruing and maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame for all poſteritie, to giue alowance to the Printing and publiſhing of the Booke, that I preſented vnto his Maieſtie, principally concerning the planting and preſeruing of wood, as hath and doth appeare to all men, whereby I am the better animated by his Maieſtie, and many other good men, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuere in ſo needefull and more then neceſſary buſineſſe, and to apply my whole indeuour, to ſeeke out all poſſible means that may be found to effect the ſame: with the leaſt charge &amp; loſſe of ground, the better to incourage all his louing Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects thereunto: by meanes whereof, together with the dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conference that I haue with many of the better ſort; and oft, for this purpoſe with Husbandmen, and workemen; who (for the moſt part) haue beſt experience in this buſineſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loath to write more then by mine owne eie-ſight I know to be true. Further, ſeeking to know the opinions and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of many vnderſtanding and good Common-wealths
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:183843:4"/> men, to ſeuerall ends; and hauing conference with ſome skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Surueyors of Land, and ſuch as take vpon them to know the number of Acres, that are contained in this Kingdome: Thus, obſeruing what I heare or ſee, tending to any publique good, eſpecially for this buſineſſe, I attaine to a neere eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation what Acres the Kingdome doth containe, what acres wil plentifully ſupply all wants, and maintaine the Kingdome for euer, being planted and preſerued, as followeth: and how as great ſtore of Fire-wood may be raiſed, being maintained, as may plentifully maintaine the Kingdome for all purpoſes, aſwell for the making of yron, and all other mettalls that the Kingdome doth affoord for euer; ſo farre from the loſſe or hurt to land, as it may rather greatly better and improue it: Firſt, it is generally decreed by all Surueyours, that the whole kingdome containeth nine and twenty millions, fiue hundred ſixty eight thouſand acres, or neere thereabouts: whereof it is ſuppoſed that there is foure millions, and al the odde thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands waſte, that yeeldeth little or no profite at all; and that there hath been within a hundred years laſt paſt, foure milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of woods and buſhy grounds, that yeelded little profit, but wood and buſhes, ouer and aboue Parkes, Forreſts, and Chaſes.</p>
                  <p>Forth of which twenty nine millions, and the odde thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, the waſtes being deducted, which in effect is fiue mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, the remainder is fiue and twenty millions: whereon wood, hath, doth, or would grow, if it were planted and preſerued: Firſt, for this purpoſe, take forth of euery thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand acres, forty foure acres, incloſe and plant the ſame according to the directions following: Whereſoeuer it lieth, plant foure acres of euery forty foure in rowes, ſo as there may be contained in a hundred thouſand acres, ſo much tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber as will plentifully ſerue the Kingdome for all vſes, euery tree to be ten yards diſtant one from an other one way, and three the other, which can be no loſſe to ſuch as ſhall plant, neither for their owne vſes, nor for ſuch as want ground to plant on; in reſpect that ſuch as want, muſt be conſtrained to buy of ſuch as haue to ſell, which is ſo farre from the loſſe of any, as it will be for their greateſt profite; for after twenty
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:183843:4"/> yeares the forty acres will yeeld much more profite, either in corne or graſſe then the foure and forty did before, ouer and aboue the benefite of the timber; and in the meane time, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no loſſe. The like planting for fire-wood might bee made in rowes, as ſhall appeare, but it is altogether neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe; for the very hedges, being planted and made as after followeth, will yeelde Fire-wood plentifully for all vſes, as by experience ſhall appeare, ſo as within thirtie yeares it may be more then needefull to haue any Copies or Spring-woods at all, but that all Wood-land may be conuerted to Tillage or Paſture, to the particular good of the Owners and Common wealth. Further, ſhewing in particular, what publique good may ariſe thereby. In the meane time, it were very conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, that the ſtocking vp of woods were preuented, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they were ſtocked vp into rowes, for it is generally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, that within a very few yeares, there will be little or no wood left for any vſe, the ſtocking &amp; ſtubbing is ſo great, notwithſtanding the Lawes prouided, by the worthy King of famous memory <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, for the preſeruing of wood; which laws haue beene from time to time continued, and are ſtill in force, and haue beene moſt earneſtly called vpon by the Kings Maieſtie euer ſince his comming to this kingdome, eſpecially at euery high Court of Parliament, where he hath not onely required the continuance thereof, but alſo moſt earneſtly giuen it in charge (eſpecially at the laſt Parliament) that ſome courſe might be taken for the planting and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of woods, which aſſuredly (as I haue heard) was inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the laſt ſitting in Parliament, the which cannot be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to ſuch as daily ſtocke and ſtubbe vp woods: neither reſpecting the diſpleaſure of his Maieſty, nor the breach of the Lawes in that caſe prouided. In euery countrey wood is daily ſtubbed vp, eſpecially within twenty miles of London, where wood is pretious, and too deare for the poorer ſort; by meanes thereof, they are conſtrained to breake hedges, to the great decaying of wood, and to the grieuance of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that hath woods &amp; hedges, and to their great charge, which I finde generally complained of, and daily more and more wil be complained of: for (ſay the poore) Though they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:183843:5"/> want victualls, that is too deare for them to get by their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt labour, yet will they not periſh for want of fire, ſo long as it is to be gotten. The beſt remedy for the ſame, is, a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Plantation, whereby no one man may feele the loſſe that ſome few do, that plant; for as they plant the one day, the poore plucke or cut them vp the next day, if not the ſame night. Which, if all men ſhould be conſtrained to plant, it would be as it is in <hi>Worceſter</hi> ſhire with fruit, where the plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is ſo great, as the ſtealing of ſome few is neuer miſſed: Euen ſo would it be by the generall planting of wood, and in time be growne ſo cheape, as the poore would rather chooſe to buy then ſteale it.</p>
                  <p>Alſo the making of yron and glaſſe, hath beene, and is the greateſt decay of wood; notwithſtanding, yron was neuer ſo ill, nor neuer ſo deare as it is at this inſtant, by the halfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo great ſtore was made in this kingdome; &amp; by all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood is likely to grow dearer: the reaſons why it is ſo deare, are eſpecially two; the one in reſpect that wood is ſo worne out, as many are conſtrained to giue ouer the making therof: which want may be ſupplied by the meanes following, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, out of hedges by lop-wood, which will approuedly make as good char-cole for all vſes, as any other wood, which may be continued ſo long as it ſhall pleaſe GOD the Kingdome ſhall endure: the other is in reſpect, that before ſo great ſtore of yron was made in this Kingdome, the Merchants bought Cloth of the Clothiers, which beyond the Seas they exchanged for yron; which was better yron, and better cheap then the Engliſh yron: the want of which exchange, together with the tranſporting of Wooll beyond the Seas, the worthy trade of clothing is ſo decayed, as many poore people that were ſet on worke by the abler ſort of Clothiers, are conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to beg, that before liued well by their labour: Alſo there are millions of people that liue in great feare, that they in a ſhort time may fall into the like neceſſity, which are the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters, the Shippe-wrights, the Plough and Cart-makers, the Ioyners, the Cowpers, and the Coach-maker. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it is generally conceiued by all men of iudgement, that enter into conſideration of the premiſſes, that without a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:183843:5"/> generall Planting and Preſeruing, both of Timber and Fire-wood be, the Kingdome by no meanes can be maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned another Age; which with ſmall coſt and labour (to wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling mindes) in good time, may be preſerued and maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as plentifully as euer heeretofore: as ſhall be proued to the glorie of God, content of his Maieſtie, their owne ſelues, poſteritie, and Common-wealth.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the Planting and Preſeruing of Timber, all men with whom I haue conuerſed, are of one minde, that a better direction then herein is ſet downe cannot bee deuiſed, which is, by planting groues of a Roode, or halfe a Roode of ground in a Groue, in paſture grounds (or as followeth,) eſpecially in Rowes, whereby much more timber may be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in leſſe ground as ſhall appeare; which being performed, there will be timber enough for al purpoſes, with the ſurpluſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Timber that may be planted and preſerued in Forreſts, Chaſes, Parks, Commons, or common Paſture, and much the better it will continue, if it be ſo prouided, that none ſhall fell or other-waies make away any tree or trees, but to be enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to plant and preſerue ſo many as ſhall be felld, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies made away. Thus may Timber be raiſed two ſeuerall waies; the one in Groues, the other in Rowes: for Groues, ſuch as haue but one hundred acres, and ſo for ſuch as haue more, to incloſe for euery hundred acres, one ſeuerall Rood in ſome corner of a Cloſe, which is already incloſed, for the ing of chrſauages, where halfe of the Fence is already made, and is to be maintained notwithſtanding this deuice; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the middeſt of a Cloſe, although the charge be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the more, where the cattell may not onely haue ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow in Summer, but alſo ſhelter in Winter, euery way the better. To improue the cloſe and cattell, the plot of ground for this purpoſe of one roode, would be in length tenne pole, in breadth foure: in which length there is contained fifty fiue yards, and in breadth twenty two yards. In which plot of ground there may be planted fiue rowes of trees for Timber, and in euery rowe there muſt bee digged vppe foureteene plots of a yard ſquare, which ſhould be digged vp two ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall times, betweene Midſummer and Michaelmaſſe; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:183843:6"/> when the meanes following are to be ſet, according to the nature of the ſoyle, and the directions following; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery plot to be foure yards diſtant euery way one from an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; ſo there may be contained in a Rood of ground three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and tenne trees. And in euery of theſe plots ſo digged, there may be ſet nine, a foote one from another, (either A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kornes, Cheſſenuts, Beech-maſte, Keyes of Aſh, Rootes or Chips of Elme) being ſo ſet, &amp; come vp, the ground would be weeded twice, or thrice the firſt and ſecond yeare, if occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſerue, and after foure or fiue yeares, when it may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned which of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is likeſt to be the beſt trees, there would be but foure left, the other would be drawne vp and plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted elſe-where at the Owners pleaſure. And after ſixeteene or twenty yeares three of the other may be felld, and made away for ſome vſes; and onely one, being the very beſt, to remaine; from which all the leaues would be plucked off by hand within a foote of the top, in the beginning of Iune, ſo long as a man can reach them, and afterwards cut off with a knife, or light forreſt bill, made for that purpoſe. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why I wiſh the planting of Groues to be in ſo many ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueralls, is, that when a Groue is felld, it ſhould be all felld: for the felling of trees in woods at ſeuerall times, hath beene a great decay to wood. And further, by experience it may be proued, that ſeldome good timber groweth of old ſtocks; by reaſon whereof, I could wiſh that trees ſhould rather bee ſtocked vp, then felld, that the ground might be planted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. The ſecond way for planting in rowes is as hereafter followeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For the planting in Barren, Champaine, or Gorſsie grounds, either for Timber or Fire-wood.</head>
                  <p>IF in all Champaine Countries, where land is barren, and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well ſo ſcant, that they are conſtrained to burne the ſtraw, and manure, which ſhould be imployed to the manuring of land; the want thereof is the vtter vndoing of many a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, who tilleth much land, ſoweth much ſeed, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth much loſſe, for want of manure. If therefore (I ſay) not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:183843:6"/> onely of my ſelfe, but alſo in the opinions of many vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding men, inhabiting in ſuch countries, that if ſome part of their bareſt grounds that lieth ſo far from the town wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto it doth belong, that ſeldome, or neuer it is manured: by reaſon whereof it oft lieth ley, and yeeldeth no profite: if for this purpoſe, there were eleuen acres of that land, as it lieth together, and that one acre of the eleuen were planted with wood in rowes, and after that rate for more or leſſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the number of the Acres that are in the poſſeſſion of the Lords of Land, and their Tenants in euery towne; which acre may thus be planted: (firſt it is to be vnderſtood, that a ſtatute acre doth containe in length 220. yards, and in breadth, two and twenty. Firſt make a good Fence, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the directions following, and then beginne at a ſide of the eleuen acres, and meaſure ten yards in breadth, and in euery eleuenth yard digge vp fiue and fifty plots of ground of a yard ſquare; and ſo in euery eleuenth yard from ſide to ſide: Euery plot to be three yards betweene one an other in the rowes, ouer and aboue the ſquare yard for fire-wood; for Timber but two yards betweene the ſquare yards, ſo as there may be three ſcore and fourteene plots in euery rowe, and ſo planted and obſerued, as before is declared. Whereby there may be contained in one acre, one thouſand ſixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and odde trees for timber: In foure acres of the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, ſixe thouſand and foure ſcore, euery tree to growe one from another tenne yards one way, and three the other; and for fire-wood, one thouſand one hundred and tenne. There may be alſo contained in one entire acre, one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand two hundred and ten trees for timber, euery one to haue foure yards of ground to thriue on.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Directions may be obſerued by ſuch as are deſirous to plant ſpacious grounds, ſo farre from the loſſe of ground, as the ground thereby may be much improoued, eſpecially if the ground be barren, by letting it lie ley foure or fiue years after it is planted; which lying will better the ground, ſo as it may be plowed between the rowes, and ſowne with corne, and for two or three yeares haue good croppes: in which time the plants will be ſo growne vp, as it may be a ſheepe-paſture,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:183843:7"/> till the wood be paſt taking hurt by cattell: in which time the ſhadow of the trees, and the rotting of leaues, and the manure of the ſheepe will better the ground, ſo as it will be good medow, paſture, or corne ground, at the Owners pleaſure, for his beſt profit. This were a very profitable courſe to be obſerued in ſheepe-walkes, on Downes, where hedge-wood is ſcant, as commonly it is in ſuch barren grounds. The beſt way to incloſe, is (if it be in ſwarthy grounds) to ſet the aforeſaid meanes as a foote-ſet of thornes without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ditch, and to raiſe the Fence of either ſide by walles of Soddes, as is to be ſeene betweene <hi>Lincolne</hi> and the Horſe-race, or as commonly ſheepe pennes are made in Downes and Heaths: If no ſwarth, by a double ditch, and ſet the meanes on the top of a banke, being made a yard broad on the top, ſo as a hedge of a foote high of either ſide will ſerue to defend it; and by a like planting in all gorſſie grounds, where gorſſe groweth ſo naturally that the Owners of the grounds can by no meanes deſtroy it: great ſtore of timber or fire-wood may be raiſed, with the other profits, and the ſoyle much improued: for after the trees be paſt taking hurt by cattell, the gorſſe betweene the rowes may be ſtocked vp, ſo as the tenne yards of ground betweene the rowes may bee ſowne with corne, and being limed when it is tilled, the lime, together with the ſhadow of the trees, will approuedly ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the gorſſe, as the ground will be recouered to be corne, medow, or paſture. In like ſort, all broomy ground may be improued. Some that haue gorſſie grounds, haue obiected, that if their gorſſe ſhould be deſtroyed, they ſhould be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified thereby, in regard they haue no better fewell. To ſuch I haue giuen good ſatisfaction, that it is not intended, that the gorſſe ſhould bee deſtroyed, before the wood bee paſt taking hurt by cattell, when the wood will yeeld better fewell, and better ſtore.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>How to improue barren ground.</head>
                  <p>THE beſt remedy for barren grounds, either for ſandy or clay, for fruit-trees, or any kind of wood, to make them grow ſpeedily, &amp; without moſſe, is for ſandy land, to make a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:183843:7"/> hole, ſo bigge, as it will holde the quantitie of three bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhells of good earth, and a buſhell of vnſlecked lime; then put into the hole a third part of the lime, and vpon that lime, lay a third part of the earth, and vpon that earth, another part of the lime, and vpon that lime a third part of earth, and ſo the reſt: and in like ſort ſand and lime for clay land, and ſo lay more or leſſe, as occaſion ſerueth. Thus mingle them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and let it lie a quarter of a yeare before it is to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and when you remooue a yong tree, or ſet a ſtocke to graffe on, lay vnder, and about the roote a buſhell of the lime and earth well mingled together, and powre thereon a paile full of water, which water will waſh the earth cloſe to euery roote. And to any kind of Peach or Plumb-ſtone halfe a pecke; and for Cheſſenuts, Akornes, or any other kinde of ſeedes of wood, vſe this mingled earth in diſcretion, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proouedly thus being vſed, they will grow more in one yeare then in any other ground in two, though the ſoile be good: and it is a ſpeciall good manuring for corne, the nature of lime is to make clay-land lighter, and ſand-land ſtiffer, as partly may appeare in buildings, that lime and ſand do make morter, when it is drie, as hard as ſtones.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For the planting of Timber-trees, or Fire-wood, in Forreſts, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Parkes, Commons, and common Paſtures.</head>
                  <p>EXperience hath, and may teach all men to know, for it is to be ſeene with the eyes of all men, that in all ages, bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes haue beene, are, and will be (if they be preſerued) in all grounds, the mother and nurſe of trees, ſo that all men may take notice thereby, that by the digging vp of a hole a foote ſquare, and three or foure fingers deepe, in the middeſt of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tuft of buſhes, gorſſe, furres, or whins, as ſome terme them, or in hollinbuſhes, and therein to ſet 3. of the maſt of oake, cheſſenuts, beech, keys of aſh, the roots, or chips of elme, or rather rootes or ſykamore ſeeds which wil grow as faſt as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other wood, the body good for little, but for to make tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, or drinking-cups, and for thoſe vſes, better then any other wood growing in this kingdom, as before is ſet down:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:183843:8"/> any of theſe, according to the nature of the ſoile, wherin theſe are to be planted: out of which three it is not to be doubted, but one of them at the leaſt, wil grow and proſper, the buſhes being preſerued about them, till the plants be paſt taking hurt by cattell. This may be performed with a ſmall charge, for a man may ſet a hundred in a day at the leaſt, by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence I ſpeake it, which can not coſt aboue twelue pence (a thouſand for ten ſhillings.)</p>
                  <p>Many there are that like wel of this planting of wood, and many doe obſerue it, that before were deſirous to raiſe wood, by taking vp of yong trees where they did grow and proſper; which are weary of that kinde of planting, by reaſon that for the moſt part, halfe of them doe not grow, which mooueth many to obſerue theſe directions: And ſome there are that ſay they like theſe directions well; but ſay they, it is againſt the nature of this Age to tarry ſo long for profite. To which I anſwer, That if the Anceſtors of noblemen, gentlemen, and others, had had ſo little reſpect to their poſterity, as we haue in this Age; there are ſome noblemen, and many others, that would haue been conſtrained to haue ſold a great part of the land their Anceſtours left them, to ſupply the wants which they haue ſupplied by their woods; and it will fall ſo out ere it be long, that ſuch muſt ſell land, for wood their Anceſtors will leaue them none to ſell: And to content ſuch, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, I haue added by experience directions for this preſent Age, as followeth towards the latter end of this Booke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For the planting of Fire-wood about Parkes.</head>
                  <p>HOw all Parkes may be fenced by fire-wood, ſo as after tenne or twelue yeares it will be ſtronger then any pale; and after forty yeares ſtronger then any wall, and longer laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by many degrees: and being once made, neuer to be made againe, with the charge and profit that may ariſe thereby. Say for this purpoſe, that there is a parke to be fenced of foure miles pale-walke, which miles containe in length thirty two furlongs of Statute-meaſure, euery furlong containeth forty poles, euery pole fiue yards and a halfe: Admit there were no ditch at all about the pale, nor wood (as commonly there
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:183843:8"/> is) and that all were to be ditched and fenced anew, with a ditch of fiue foote wide at the top, a foote and a halfe broade in the bottome, and three foot deepe, and that this ditch, with the getting and ſetting of the meanes aforeſaid, for the plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of timber, ſhould coſt twelue pence a pole; the totall of the charge three ſcore and three pounds at the moſt: for it is certaine, that much of this may be ſaued: for in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the ditch cannot be ſo chargeable; for about many parks in ſome places, there need no ditch at all, and in ſome places, a leſſe ditch will ſerue. Neither can the hedging be charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in two reſpects; the one, by reaſon that about many Parkes, there are many thornes growing, which being felld to make the fence once, will afterwards ſo grow vp, as they will defend the wood ſo ſet without any further charge; and about many parkes there is as much wood growing as will defray the charge: ſo as to ſome the effecting of this buſines, will be little or no charge at all. The earth of this new ditch muſt be caſt to the pale-ward, ſo as the banke may be a yard broad on the top: fence there needeth none, but long buſhes ſo put betweene the pales aboue the railes, as they may reach and hang ouer the banke into the ditch.</p>
                  <p>This being done, for ſuch ſoiles as by experience Maſte and Seeds will beſt like of, as may beſt appeare by the wood thereon growing, the Maſte would be gathered as it falleth from the tree, and not beaten downe before it be ripe. The Aſh keyes may be gathered about Alhollontide: being thus gotten and gathered in, they would be kept neyther too wet nor too drie, till they be ſet, according to the directions fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. The rootes of Elme are to be gotten by baring olde Elmes at the roote, betweene Alhollontide and Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſſe, when the ſappe of trees is in the rootes, from whence there may be taken, without hurt to the Elme, many yoong rootes of the bigneſſe of a little finger, and a foot long. And as of Elme, ſo of Wiche, being a wood as apt to grow ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily as any other, which are to be cut from the olde rootes. Theſe yong roots would be ſet as a foot-ſet of thornes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a foote of the pale, ſo as the thornes may hang ouer them; ſet in the ground, and one inch out of the ground: ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:183843:9"/> in the ſides of banks, as quick-ſets, they are to be ſet in 2. rowes, 3. fingers broad betweene the rowes, and ſo ſet as they may not ſtand directly one againſt another. The maſte and ſeedes would alſo be ſo ſet in two rowes, three fingers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene euery rowe, three fingers deepe, and foure in a foot in either rowe. The boughes of Elme, Willows, or Sallow, would bee lopped from the trees betweene mid-March and the middeſt of Aprill, when the ſappe is in them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the leaues put foorth; they would be of three or foure yeares growth, of the freſheſt, ſappieſt, and knottiew. Thus being lopped from the trees, they would be cut in length of a foote long, colt-footed at either end, the boughes and twigges being cut off cloſe to the body: they would bee laid in trenches in two rowes, three fingers deepe, with the knotty ſide vpward, and three fingers betweene the rowes a hand breadth one from an other, and couered with earth, which is neither weedy nor graſſie. Theſe boughs would be laid the ſame day that they are lopped, or the next day after at the fartheſt, or ſet in the ground as ſets a foote deepe.</p>
                  <p>This being done, they will within ſixe or ſeuen yeares bee growne ſo high, as the plants may be bended, and laied as a plaſhed hedge, but not cut at the rootes: the reaſon is, that being ſo yong the plants will eaſily bend, which way a man will haue them, and when they are to be laid, the rowe that is to be laid, would be ſhread cloſe to the body, and topped ſo high as when they are laid, the toppe may lie ſeuen foote wide from the roote, and ſo high as a beaſt may not reach the tops: And when the rowe is in laying, if they grow thicker then a foote aſunder, ſome may be cut vp for bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to binde them downe that are laide, for thicker then a foote aſunder is needeleſſe for them to be laide. The other rowe would be yearely ſhread, and kept with ſmall tops, the leſſer to hurt the Fence ſo laid, and ſome of them are to be bound into the fence ſo laid, to ſtand three or foure yeares for ſtakes, ſo as thoſe that are thus bound downe after two or three yeares, will continue ſo, and lie as railes; and if cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell bee kept from the browſing of them but a yeare: the boughes will ſpring foorth of the knots, ſo as the Fence will
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:183843:9"/> be both thicke and ſtrong, and much the ſtronger, by the helpe of the other rowe, which after the fence of it ſelfe is growne ſtrong, may be felled and imployed to other vſes. This in common reaſon (as I ſaid before) cannot but in ten or twelue yeares be a ſtronger Fence then any pale, and in a ſhort time ſtronger then any wall, and longer laſting, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further charge. And this for experience, in part, may be ſeene in all wood-land countries, eſpecially in Fences about Woods, where it is to be ſeene, that for want of thornes in many places all kinde of woods are plaſhed, and thus laide, which in ſome places haue laine ſo long, as they are growne ſo great, that they are incorporated one into another; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding liketh very well, and yeeldeth much fire-wood by lopping off the toppes and boughs that are growne forth of them ſo lying.</p>
                  <p>And as in this, ſo in other things, by experience I write of that which mine eyes haue ſeene in many places for two or three poles together, where there haue beene fiue or ſixe heads growing out of one tree ſo laide. And for the better proofe hereof, I haue alſo ſeene, as I haue rode by the way, in an Orchard (in little <hi>Waltham</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> foure miles at the moſt from <hi>Chelmsford,</hi>) an Apple tree that was blowne downe many yeares ſince, which lieth cloſe to the ground, the root hauing ſome ſmall holde in the ground, which hath put forth of the body ſo lying, fiue trees at the leaſt, which are ſo nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed as they beare fruit. I haue alſo ſeene in a towne within two miles of <hi>Stone</hi> in <hi>Stafford</hi> ſhire, in a ground of maiſter <hi>Ratliffes,</hi> a Peare-tree that was likewiſe blowne downe, big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then a fadome about, that ſtood in a hedge, which tree li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a yard from the ground, being ſtaied ſo by two boughs that ſticke in the ground, which hath ſo taken roote, as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, with the helpe eſpecially of ſome part of the roote, that it hath alſo put forth, and nouriſheth fiue trees as bigge as the calfe of a mans legge, which grow a yard one from another; whereby it may the better appeare, that this kinde of Fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing may bee perfourmed, not onely with wood, but alſo with Apple and Peare-trees, if neede required, with ſuch as like thereof, to the good of themſelues and common-wealth.</p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:183843:10"/>
                  <p>Another kinde of fencing there is, that many do like bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of, then the laying of the wood, as is aforeſaid, which by experience may be performed by letting the plants grow, and neuer to lay them, but yearely to ſhread the twigs of the one rowe, that after is to be felld, ſo as they may be kept with ſmall toppes, the leſſe to hurt thoſe that are to remaine for the Fence, which rowe that is to ſtand for the Fence, would be topped at ſixeteene or twenty yeares growth, fifteene or ſixteene foote high from the ground, and againe after eight yeares, and then for the better encreaſing of fire-wood they would be ſo lopped, as there may be as well three heads of a tree, as one, and euery head to yeeld as much wood, as if there were but one head of the tree: if when the worke-man doth top a tree, he would top it where the tree putteth forth moſt boughes, within three inches aboue the knottieſt place of the tree, not too flatte, as many worke-men doe, but ſloping, the leſſe to take water for the rotting of the tree: at which ſecond lopping, all the boughes would bee lopped off cloſe to the head of the tree, but onely three of the greateſt; the one that groweth directly vp, to bee topped halfe a yard aboue the head of a tree; the other two would be of thoſe that growe outward, from either ſide of the tree from the rowe-ward, the leſſe to hurt the rowe by dropping: which two would be lopped foure foote off from the body of the tree, by which meanes, as well from this, as from the other kind of fencing, there may be lopped from a Parke of foure miles pale, yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, after one and twenty yeares, two furlongs of ſixeteene yeares growing; and as in euery pole there was ſixteene let to grow, ſo there are ſixteene to be yearely lopped, which being husbanded, as aforeſaid, would yeeld eight and forty heads, whereas if they ſhould haue but one head a peece (as they haue three) could not yeelde leſſe then three loades of wood in a pole of ſixteene yeares growing; worth to be ſold two ſhillings ſixe pence the loade, ariſeth to tenne pounds a yeare. The timber for paling and workemanſhip yearely ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, which can not be leſſe worth then ſixe pounds, (which timber is more then needefull to he ſaued) beſides the profite of the browſe for Decre) maſte for hogges, and barke for the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:183843:10"/> tanning of leather, which would ariſe to be much worth, if the wood might grow vntill it be twenty or foure and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares olde, which then would alſo yeelde many good ſparres for the building of out-houſes and cottages, with good ſtore of worke for poore laboring men, by lopping and faggoting the wood. This direction were very profitable to be vſed about ſpring-woods when they fell their wood, and make their hedges, ſo as it may be made once for euer to great profite. What reaſon any man hath to omit this, I leaue to be cenſured by the diſcreet Reader.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For the increaſe of Fire-wood, by the Lopping of trees.</head>
                  <p>FOr the better increaſing of wood by lopping of trees, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience will teach all men to know, that will obſerue it, as hee rideth on the way in euery Countrey, eſpecially in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> neere vnto the <hi>Wiches,</hi> (where ſalt is made, and much wood is ſpent by the boyling thereof,) that euery tree will as well yeelde fiue or ſixe heads, as one, if workemen, when they loppe trees, would obſerue the directions before ſet downe, for the topping and lopping of trees about parks, and in hedges.</p>
                  <p>For the increaſing of fire-wood in hedge-rowes, between decayed trees, the beſt remedy is, that when ſuch trees decay, and haue lop-wood on them, of the age of tenne or twelue yeares, within a weeke of the firſt day of Auguſt, or within a weeke after, when the ſappe is in the tops of the trees, to ſet a diſcreete workeman into the trees, and there with a ſharpe knife to cut off cloſe to the head of the trees, all the barke a hand broad that groweth vpon the principall boughs that be likeſt to make trees, ſo cleane that he leaueth not the breadth of a haire, but rather cut part of the wood then leaue any of the barke: This being done, preſently get good clay, and let one worke it to the breadth and thickneſſe of a tile, and ſo long, or longer, as it may well lappe about the bough ſo pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, then lay thereon ſome fatte earth two or three fingers thicke, and lay the ſame clay and earth vpon the barke of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:183843:11"/> bough next to the plot ſo pared; and with moſſe and bands binde theſe ſame on, like vnto a graffe, and ſo let it reſt, and about Alhollontide, then make holes in the ground where you would haue them to grow, and preſently ſaw off with a hand-ſaw the boughs ſo clayed, betweene the clay and the plot ſo pared, and ſo doe it as the earth be not ſhaken off, carry them, and ſet them halfe a yard deepe, fill vp the holes with limed earth halfe a yard broade about the plant and treade it well; if the ground be barren, make the holes ſo much the wider, and fill them: Being ſo ſet, ſtake them, and binde them as other Sets, and aſſuredly they will grow and proſper better then other Sets, or tranſplanted trees: If they be ſet betweene trees, loppe the olde trees before you ſet them, that they be not ouer-topped, nor dropped by them: theſe being either elme, willow, or ſallow. As for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wood, I haue ſeene no experience (but of ſome boughs of Apple and Peare-trees, which being thus vſed, haue borne fruit the ſame yeare they were ſet,) I can finde no reaſon to the contrary, but that other woods may grow and proſper as well as theſe. This is the moſt ſpeedy way to beget woods.</p>
                  <p>All theſe Directions beeing obſerued, there may bee in good time, more timber, fire-wood, corne and catell contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this kingdome, then hath beene at any time theſe three-ſcore yeares, and yet no woods at all: ſo that the ſoile of all woods in time may be conuerted to tillage, medow, or paſture, to the profite of the Kings maieſty, all Poſterity, and the Common-wealth. The kingdome thereby may bee the better defended from forren enemies by the Nauigation, the bankes of the Seas, and ebbing and flowing riuers defended, ſtaies maintained; all which cannot bee maintained but by wood, without which defence a great part of the kingdome is in danger to be ouer-flowen and ruinated: ſome proofes thereof were to be ſeene this yeare one thouſand ſix hundred and thirteene, neare <hi>Blackewall,</hi> where was a Breach that hath and will coſt two thouſand pounds to recouer it: And this winter, to the vtter vndoing of many an able man, in many places of this kingdom: the charge of ſtaies and banks in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ebbing and flowing riuers, is chargeable to many, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:183843:11"/> in the riuer of <hi>Owes,</hi> where the maintaining of ſtaies and bankes coſteth the Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> at the leaſt a hundred markes a yeare, and is very chargeable to ſir <hi>Thomas Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam;</hi> and all that haue grounds there, that are charged there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, according to the proportion of their grounds. The decay of theſe bankes may in one tide drowne much land, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny townes: which the obſeruing of theſe directions, &amp; ſome other following, will preuent.</p>
                  <p>The wood that may be raiſed about parkes, and the hedges within this kingdome, would raiſe many profites to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, as the making of yron, and all other kinde of mettalls which the kingdome affoordeth, together with the burning of lime for the manuring of land, and buildings, and burning of bricke and tile for building, with many other profites to the kingdome.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For the increaſing of wood in the Springs of wood.</head>
                  <p>VVHereas in ſprings I find many waſte places growne ouer with graſſe, by reaſon whereof, men couet to put in Calues and Horſes, which are great ſpoiles to woods. The onely way to furniſh ſuch places, eſpecially in barren grounds, which may beſt be ſpared for wood, vntill ſuch time that the other woods be growne vp, is either when the Spring is fiue or ſixe yeares growne, or when it is felld, to digge vp certaine ſquare yards, according to the ſpaciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ground, three yards betweene euery plot, and therein to ſet, or lay in trenches the aforeſaide meanes, as is before ſet downe; and when they are growne vp fiue or ſixe yeares to plaſh them cloſe by the ground, and lay them in Trenches euery way from the roote three fingers deepe, and to couer them with earth, and ſo of all other wood that gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth of olde rootes, ſo as there may not be a waſte place nor any thornes left to grow, but proouing wood.</p>
                  <p>As for other grounds that are woorth twenty ſhillings an Acre yearely, (which is too good for wood to grow on) but
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:183843:12"/> that the decay of wood is too great, I could wiſh that it were ſtocked into rowes, either for timber, or to top and lop it for fire-wood.</p>
                  <p>And whereas it is required by the lawe, that there ſhould be a certaine number of trees preſerued for timber, which is by few men performed, the reaſon is, that the dropping and ſhadow of them will deſtroy the vnder-wood, which is moſt true: my aduice is, that rather the number of timber-trees might be preſerued in ſome corner of the Spring, where they may be preſerued from many dangers which they are ſubiect to, as they are left in the Springs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Concerning the planting of wood in hedges already made with thornes.</head>
                  <p>SOme do obiect, that the planting of wood in them will ſo deſtroy the thornes by the dropping and ouerſhadowing of them, as there will be no good fence kept. To ſuch I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that if they would the next yeare after that they cauſe a hedge to be plaſhed, &amp; the ditch thereunto belonging ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſome ſmall quantity of the earth caſt vp to the roots of the hedge; for too much earth ſo caſt to the rootes of the hedge decay the hedge, and that they would ſet in the ſame earth ſuch meanes as is before ſet downe, and ſo vſe them, they might at any time after twenty yeares, haue both good ſtore of wood and thorns, and alſo haue a ſtronger fence then any thornes can make. The charge of the ſetting and getting of the meanes in common reaſon can no way coſt two ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings a furlong, for two men will ſet at the leaſt two furlongs a day, the one man to make holes to ſet them in, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to put in the meanes, and couer it. The profite that may ariſe thereby is before ſet downe for the profite of parkes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Concerning ſuch as hereafter may incloſe.</head>
                  <p>IS to incloſe with the aforeſaid means, and not with thorns, whereby with leſſe charge &amp; labour they may raiſe a fence ſtronger and longer laſting, with greater profit, by the ſetting
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:183843:12"/> of the aforeſaide meanes, on the top of the bankes, as is ſet downe for Parkes, which (by experience) will grow more ſpeedily then thornes, and make a better fence, (as is proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) that will with a good Gate, Locke, and Key, keepe all Cattell ſafe from ſtealing, and from breaking into any other grounds then the owner would haue them, ſafe from treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to his neighbour, or his neighbours to him; whereby much corne may be ſaued, treſpaſſing preuented (which too often raiſeth enuy, and ſuites in Lawe.) The browſe of the wood in winter will greatly relieue cattell, and ſaue fodder: And being wood that will yeelde maſte, the maſte will be very beneficiall to the particular Owner, and Common-wealth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Directions for ſuch as are deſirous to ſtocke vp woods, for the improouing of the Soile.</head>
                  <p>BY conuerting of the ſame to corne, medow, or paſture, &amp; to haue as much, or rather more profite by the woods, then they had before; is, firſt, to leaue a yard in breadth round about the ſides, for the maintaining of the fence, which may be made once for all, by obſeruing the aforeſaid directions: Then beginne at a ſide next to the wood ſo left, and ſtocke vp all the wood whatſoeuer, ſo as the ground may bee plowed tenne yards in breadth, and in the eleuenth yard ſtocke vp all but fifty fiue of the beſt trees, which trees would (as neere as may be) be ſo left, that they may grow foure yards diſtant one from another, from end to end, as trees planted in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard: and ſo ſtocke vp from ſide to ſide, and from end to end, leauing the like diſtance, ſo as there may be ten yards diſtance one way, and foure an other from tree to tree: by which meanes, in euery two rowes, there may be left an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and tenne trees out of euery Acre, how great or little ſoeuer the ground be: which being topped, and after twelue yeares lopped, with many heads (as they may be by the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions already ſet downe, or rather for a greater profite, left vnlopped till the wood be of twenty yeares growth) the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite thereof, by the greatnes of the wood, and the barke, with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:183843:13"/> the profite of the wood that may ariſe about the fence (being made as before is directed) will farre exceed the profite of the vnder-wood growing of all the ground before.</p>
                  <p>But as the caſe ſtandeth, and as is more like to ſtand, by the want of timber, if all the trees were left for timber, and neuer topped nor lopped, would, in time, ariſe to the greater pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite; eſpecially if they were euery third yeare ſhread in March, when the ſappe is riſing vp, and the wood worth the ſhread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which ſappe would ſo grow, as it would couer the knottes, by which meanes the trees will grow taper-like, with ſo ſmall tops, as the ground betweene the rowes may be plowed three yeares, and may be laide to graſſe for nine yeares; ſo may you haue from time to time three yeares good corne, and nine yeares good graſſe, and neuer to decay the land, but rather to improue it. The trees beeing thus kept with ſmall toppes, can neither hurt corne or graſſe, by drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping or ſhadow.</p>
                  <p>Some doe obiect and ſay, that if all Spring-woods were ſo ſtocked, how ſhould hurdles be gotten for the folding of ſheepe? To which I anſwer with experience, where wood is not lopped too young, ſome of the greateſt boughes being lopped and barked, and then laide in water a moneth, they will be ſo rated, and grow ſo hard, as wormes can no way hurt them: and beeing ſo vſed, will make farre better and ſtronger hurdles, then any young rods whatſoeuer, as may appeare in many Countries of this kingdome where wood is ſo ſcant, as they are of neceſſity conſtrained to vſe willow boughs for ſpars and laths for many houſes, and to vſe them about ploughs, carts, and harrowes.</p>
                  <p>Others do obiect, that the graſſe in ſuch wooddy grounds will be ſo ſowre as cattel wil not like of it. To that I anſwer, that if the rowes be planted Eaſt and Weaſt, or ſo ſtocked, as the ground betweene the rowes may haue the morning, noon and euening Sunne, the paſture will be as ſweet as any other: the corne will as well like of it as of any other ground, and will as well drie when it is cut, or if the cattell bee put into ſuch grounds before they taſte of a ſweeter graſſe, they will like as well of that graſſe as of any other. And for the better
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:183843:13"/> proofe thereof: Who euer ſaw graſſe loſt for the eating, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny forreſt, chaſe or parke, where trees grow thicke, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the cattell in ſuch grounds, (if they be not eaten too bare) like very well, by reaſon of the ſhadow in Summer, and ſhelter in Winter.</p>
                  <p>A further experience may be taken, to incourage all men hereunto, from about thouſands of towns in this kingdome, where are to be ſeene little cloſes, of two, three, foure or fiue acres of ground, as haue ſo much timber or fire-wood grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about them, as if it were at this inſtant to be ſold, would giue more money then the fee-ſimple of the land. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it followeth, very fittingly for this purpoſe, to ſhew what good may ariſe to the particular owners of ground, by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing theſe directions ſet downe in ſundry places for theſe purpoſes, and how the kingdome may be improoued, onelie by wood planted about Parkes, and in Hedges made, and heereafter to be made of wood, ſo farre from the loſſe of any, as it may be to the generall good of all men, euen to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pooreſt, whoſe reliefe I greatly deſire.</p>
                  <p>And for my further experience, I ſawe about Chriſtmas laſt, a cloſe of ſandie Land of foure Acres, taken in the middeſt of a field belonging to <hi>Downam</hi> in <hi>Norffolke,</hi> about forty yeares agoe, and ſet round about when it was taken in, with young ſets, (as it was confeſſed to me by the Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thereof) of Aſhe, rootes of Elme, and Thornes, and the moſt part of the ſtakes of the Hedge, were of Willow and Sallow, which Stakes and Settes of Wood did ſo take roote, as vpon my credite there is growing about the ſaide cloſe fiue hundred fiftie and odde trees, of the aforeſaide wood, whereof the Owner confeſſed vnto mee that hee did euery yeare loppe fiue and fiftie of tenne yeares growing, the which wood hee could yearely ſell for forty ſhillings, and the foure Acres of ground hee could not let for aboue ſixe and twentie ſhillings and eight pence yearely: So that I doe find by experience, that the moſt ſure way to performe this planting, is to make nurſeries, which may be kept from Mice by trappes.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:183843:14"/>
                  <p>And that the ſimpleſt may the better vnderſtand it, admit for this purpoſe, that a man haue ſixe ſcore Acres of ground in his owne occupation, and that it were equally diuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to twelue Cloſes, and that but halfe the Fences about thoſe twelue Cloſes did belong vnto them, by reaſon that they are ioyning to other mens Cloſes, (as commonly all incloſed grounds are) there remaineth to euerie of thoſe Cloſes, an end, and a ſide, at the leaſt, of the Fence, which containe two furlongs, which is foure-ſcore poles to a Cloſe; all which hedges being planted, according to the directions ſet downe for hedges, there will ariſe about theſe twelue Cloſes foure and twenty furlongs, whereby the Owner of thoſe Cloſes, may after thirty yeares, loppe yearely the wood about one Cloſe, being two furlongs, or one furlong of foure and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares growth; which is the greater profite by much, by reaſon that the wood being growne ſo great, it would yeeld ſparres for the building of barnes, ſtables, cottages, and ſuch like ſtraw-thatched houſes, with good ſtore of Barke for the tanning of leather, with a greater plentie of Maſte, then being lopped yonger, it would yeelde, with many other profites to the Owner thereof, and to the good of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</p>
                  <p>The Maſte that may ariſe by this generall planting, will ſaue more corne (in thoſe yeares that it taketh) then the wit of man can imagine it to be worth. A late experience there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of may bee taken from the yeare of our Lord one thouſand ſixe hundred and eleuen, by the Maſte that the ſmall quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of wood that is left, yeelded that yeare: which Maſte fed ſo many hogges that yeare, as it greatly eaſed the priſes of corne, and other victualls. For the better proofe thereof, it is certaine, vpon confident report of ſeuerall honeſt men, that there was ſaued (by Maſte) in ſome one towne in <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester</hi>-ſhire, forty quarters of beanes and peaſe; and in ſome townes more, and in ſome leſſe: which hogges were driuen into Shropſhire to Maſte, which in former Ages was a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon courſe, before woods were deſtroyed, for the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paine Countries, to feede their hogges in wood-land coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:183843:14"/> In which times the Officers of Noblemen and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men tooke twenty or thirty pounds a yeare, for the feeding of hogges in a Parke, or in a Wood, which hardly now take fiue pounds; and in many Parkes or Woods, not one penny, the woods are ſo made away.</p>
                  <p>So (to conclude) he that obſerueth the aforeſaid directions about the twelue Cloſes, may yearely loppe eight ſcore load of wood, of twelue yeares growing, woorth to be ſolde at two ſhillings ſixe pence the load, twentie pounds, and much more, if the cloſes be leſſe. Whereby it appeareth, that all Grounds incloſed, and that heereafter may be incloſed, may be improoued three ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and foure pence an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre yearely.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="directions">
               <pb facs="tcp:183843:15"/>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:183843:15"/>
               <head>A ſecond Direction, for the preſent encreaſing of Fire-wood, agreeable to the nature of this Age, <date>1613. February 1.</date>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Earing daily, shat this more then neceſſary buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is much deſired to be effected, the ſubiects thereof much commended, and the daily deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of woods greatly complained of. In reſpect that ſo many, contrary to the Law for preſeruing of wood, and his Maieſties earneſt and daily derſire for the plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and preſeruing thereof, notwithſtanding doe ſo ſtocke vp, and other wayes deſtroy woods, as it is generally feared by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good men, that in ſhort time, there will be neither timber nor fire-wood left for any vſe. And finding one of the greateſt hinderances to this buſineſſe, to be the nature of this Age, that men may not indure to tarry ſo long for profit, till timber may be raiſed: in regard thereof, ſtil hoping that I am animated by God, who is the Author of all things that good is, and as it doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the Kings moſt excellent Maieſty, and induced by many good men by ſeuerall meanes, I haue by diligent obſeruing what I heare, and the experience that I daily ſee (and is to be ſeene, by as many as will be mindfull thereof) I haue herein ſet downe ſuch profitable directions, as already hath moued ſome, and I hope hereafter will moue all men to the obſeruing of them, both for timber and fire-wood.</p>
               <p>In reſpect that it will appeare, that there is not many deuices to improue grounds, to ſo preſent and continuall profit cleare, all charges defrayed, and for the better vnderſtanding thereof, as before, ſo heere; I do giue further knowledge to all men for this purpoſe, that there is contained in a Statute Acre of land 4840.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:183843:16"/> ſquare yards of ground, the length therof 220. yards, the breadth 22. which is 66. foote, admit for this purpoſe, and after that rate for more or leſſe, as men are diſpoſed, either for their owne vſe, or for ſale, that a man would incloſe eight Acres of earable field<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land (or plant in a cloſe of eight Acres already incloſed) the land being of the yearely value of fiue ſhillings an Acre, or not aboue a noble, where the ſoile is two foote deepe or leſſe, or of any commons, heaths or downes. Firſt, to the principal point (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which, and for want thereof, many good beginnings end in nothing) this ground muſt be firſt ditched on either ſide before Allhollantide, with a ditch two yards broad at the top, a yard and halfe deep, and a foot broad, or leſſe in the bottome, which ditch ſides and ends will take ſomething more then the third part of an Acre. The ſide ditches being made as afore, beginne and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from the edge of the ditch in the inſide of the cloſe twelue foot in breadth into the cloſe-ward, and plow vp two furrowes along from end to end by the earth, caſt foorth of the ditch as ſtreight as may be, one, one way, the other, the other way, (plow cleane, but not deepe) ſtill plow vp two ſurrowes, and leaue two foot vnplowed, till it be ſo plowed within two and twenty yards of the other ſide, and ſo leaue that two and twenty yards to plant the meanes for to raiſe timber, if the Owner pleaſe, if not, plow on till all be plowed to the earth, caſt forth of the other ditch, and at Candlemaſſe plow in the two furrowes againe very deepe, ſo as they may lie as little ridges full two foot broad on the toppe, and two foote betweene euery ridge, then preſently ditch vp the ends as the ſides, and leaue one gate-ſtead for carts or waines, to paſſe into the woods, and betweene Michaelmaſſe and Allhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantide, when Akornes, Cheſnuts, and Beech-maſte is ripe, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them as they fall from the trees, for being beaten downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they cannot ſo well growe and proſper; and it is one ſpeciall cauſe where many is ſowne or ſet, and ſo few come to perfection, if the ſoile be beſt for Elme, then the chips or roots of Elme, but ſpecially the roots, being ſet as quicke for timber, but not for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-wood.</p>
               <p>Theſe maſts muſt be got and kept drie in tubs in the ground, with ſome very drie ſand ſo put among them, as ſome ſand may be betweene euery of them, ſome do make holes in dry ground,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:183843:16"/> and keepe them therein, being well couered, to keepe them drie, and ſo keepe them till mid-March, that corne is in ſowing in the fields, and the mice returned to fields (which mice this yeare, by experience, I finde to be the greateſt enemy to the increaſing of wood that is, for this yeare they haue eaten Akornes that were lapt in haire and tarre) and then ſet, ſowe, and vſe them, according to the directions.</p>
               <p>The Aſh-keyes and Sekamore ſeeds, may be pulled or beaten downe when they are ripe &amp; drie, and kept on heaps on boorded floores, they muſt be turned ouer ſometimes, elſe they wil mold, and in like ſort ſowe them in March, and beginne and ſowe them all ouer the earth, caſt forth of the ditch, round about the cloſe, and all ouer euery ridge, as thicke as Beanes, and harrow them in, or rather couer them with an yron-toothed rake.</p>
               <p>And further, to furniſh vp the rows ſo plowed, and the banks, there muſt be alſo got immediatly after the Lady day, or before, as the Spring time falleth forth, ſo as they may be ſet before the leaues put forth, when the moſt ſap is in them fifteene ſcore wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low or ſallow ſetts of ten foot long of the freſheſt and greeneſt, which muſt be carefully carried for bruiſing of the barke, forth of euery ſet of that length there may be cut ſix ſets of halfe a yard long, cut colt-footed at both ends, which muſt be ſet in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the ridges, where the Aſh keyes are ſowne two yards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder one from an other, from end to end, foureteene inches deepe, and foure inches aboue ground. The holes wherein they are to be ſet, muſt be made with a ſpade, full foureteene inches deepe, two foote wide, the ſetts being put into the holes ſo deep, the leſſe earth muſt be put in, but neither ſtones nor graſſe, and troden cloſe to the ſets, being thus ſet, how can they in common reaſon faile but grow? for euery deaw that falleth will nouriſh them, and keepe them ſo moyſt, as they will grow more in two yeares, then an ordinary long ſet will doe in three, and the Aſh-keyes will grow ſo thicke, as they will keepe the ground conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually moiſt. There muſt be alſo ſet in like ſort two rowes of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and ſallow betweene the edge of the ditch, and the firſt ridge, the one foure foot off the firſt ridge, the other foure foot off that, and ſo on the other banke of the other ſide, if it be not planted for timber, by which meanes there may bee contained
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:183843:17"/> ſixteene rowes in euery acre, and in euery row a hundred and ten willow and ſallow plants, which in Iune after they be 3 yeares olde, all the vnder boughes muſt be cut away, and onely foure left of euery roote of the ſtraiteſt and talleſt, the vnder-boughes will be ſpringes and rods for Thechars, and the worſt good fewel for baking and brewing, which will be more worth then the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
               <p>The number of willow and ſallow poles, being foure of euery roote, is ſeuen thouſand and forty, and when the Aſh and Seka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mores are three yeares olde, they muſt be all drawne vp, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tenne of the Aſhes left to grow a foote from euery willow or ſallow, a foot aſunder one from an other euery way in the rowes, and at the ends and ſides all muſt be drawne vp, and onely three rowes left to grow vpon a foote and a halfe of ground vpon the ditch bankes, round about the cloſe for a fence, halfe a foote off the hedge of the banke, and halfe a foot aſunder one from another euery way, not ſo cloſe as they may grow directly one againſt an other, but ſo as they may fulfill the open places of each other in the rowes, and as they grow great, that one row may be the fence, the other rowes may be felld in Iune, ſo as they may growe no more, and thoſe that doe remaine for the fence muſt be topped when they are growne ſo high as the bodies may be fiue yeards high from the ground, and ſo to ſtand as pales, which will be as ſtrong a fence as any wall, being thus topped, they would be lopped after fiue yeares growth, before the wood be too high for ſhaking them looſe at the rootes by wind, and afterwards at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery tenne yeares, being lopped, as before is directed, will yeeld euery ten yeares, at the leaſt, three loade of wood of a pole. The yoong Aſhes and Sekamores that are to be drawne vp, muſt bee drawne in the new of the moone, the wind being South or Weſt, and preſently ſet, the toppes of the Aſhes being cut off as quicke, and ſet in the bottome of thorne hedges, halfe a foote aſunder, which being defended by the thornes, will be in a few yeares a very profitable and an euerlaſting fence, or being ſet vnder bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes that may defend them, will ſoone grow to be trees; or being ſet as quicke where men do incloſe, will ſooner be a fence then thornes, and raiſe more profit by many degrees, as doth appeare, and more eaſily may be conceiued.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:183843:17"/>
               <p>The number of the aſh poles in ſeuen acres is ſeuenteene thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand and ſix hundred, the totall of all the poles contained in one acre, is foure and twenty thouſand ſix hundred and forty, rated at ſix pence the ſcore, when they are ſeuen yeares old, ariſe to thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pounds, ſixeteene ſhillings an acre euery ſeuen yeares, at the leaſt (ouer and aboue the wood that will ariſe about the fence, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery willow and ſallow ſet was worth a penny forty yeares ſince, and three poles wil make two better faggots then euer were ſold in <hi>London</hi> for pence a peece theſe fifty yeares, the toppes of the poles will make good bauins, more worth then all the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip, and by other meanes there may be more made.</p>
               <p>This wood muſt be all felld and carried off the ground before the end of March, for hindering the Spring. The eight acre may be all plowed from end to end into one land, leauing a yard of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, one from the ditch, the other from the laſt ridge of that ſide, then beginne at either ſide of that acre, a yard off that end, where the gate is not to be ſet, and ſet a yard, as before is dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted for timber, and ſo ſet from end to end, and from ſide to ſide all that acre, alwayes leauing one yard euery way, and ſet an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by which means there may be raiſed in that one acre twelue hundred and ten trees for timber, euery tree to haue foure yards of ground to grow on: if they grow too thicke, it is eaſier to take ſome away, then to put more to, which being kept (as before) will grow cleane without knots taper-like, with ſo ſmall tops, as if they ſhould grow in rows, they will neuer hurt wood or corne by ſhaddow or dropping.</p>
               <p>And if the owner of the ground liſt to raiſe more Aſh plants, all the whole cloſe may be plowed and ſowne with keyes or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes, and raked in. Many there are that deſire to raiſe wood by a very vnprofitable courſe, by remoouing yong trees from the ground where they grow and proſper, and ſets them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine where 10 of 20 neuer grow: the ſpeciall reaſons, are in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that they are either remoued vnto a worſe ſoile, or too long vnſet after they are taken vp, or not ſet with the ſame ſide to the Sunne that was before, or not being taken vp in due time, about the middeſt of September, before the ſappe be returned to the roote (for as trees grow vpward in Summer, ſo doe trees grow in the rootes in winter) or not liking, grow hide-bound; the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:183843:18"/> helpe to that is, to ſlitte them from toppe to roote foure ſlitts in the barke, in Aprill, the winde being weſt or ſouth) or ſet deeper then before, or not maintained with ſtakes and buſhes, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue them from winde and cattell, or being when they are new ſet, ſtolne or ſhaken looſe at the rootes, by the poore that intend to ſteale them; And many there be that are very deſirous to plant, and ſome that would preſerue that which is planted, are diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by the poore that do cut it forth of the ſprings, breake their hedges, and euery way ſpoile &amp; ſteale; whereupon ariſeth a great grieuance betweene ſuch as haue wood, and the poore: the one will haue it, (as they ſay) although they die for it; the other will deſtroy it, though they and their poſteritie repent it: the only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy is, a generall plantation.</p>
               <p>If the whole kingdome were to be incloſed, by the ſowing of theſe grounds all ouer with the aforeſaid maſte and ſeeds of wood (but not of ſykamore, for they will not prooue ſo well after they are cut, as other wood) they muſt be ſet with the toppes) there would be ſets enow ſoone gotten, to incloſe all; and if a third part of all the ground incloſed, and hereafter to be incloſed, were continually kept in tillage, it would be the greateſt benefit to the King and kingdome that can be deuiſed, there would be more corne, bieues, muttons, butter and cheeſe, by many degrees, then there is, and much more worke for labouring men: and for fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, timber, and corne, wee ſhould exceed all Nations; ſome ſcantling may be taken therof in euery county of this kingdome, where the bareſt grounds incloſed doe (in profite) farre exceede the beſt vallies; the people much the richer, and abler of body to ſerue their Prince, and defend their countrey, and the kingdome ſecurer from inuaſion then champaine countries: The Aſhe and Sykamore ſets that may be raiſed foorth of euery Acre, will pay for the willow and ſallow ſets.</p>
               <p>If any would plant lowe grounds, the willow and ſallow ſetts muſt be ſo long, as the water may ſeldome or not at all ſtand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the heads of the ſets; in ſuch grounds they may be ſet but a yard aſunder, ſo as there may be raiſed foure thouſand eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and forty plants, but not any otherwood: if the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boughes, (as before) be cut away, and only foure left at the firſt felling: afterwards, as the rootes grow broader, there may bee
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:183843:18"/> more left. The taking away of the vnder-boughes will greatly improoue the reſt. And whereas ſome make doubt, that willow and ſallow will not grow vpon drie ground, or on any ſoile. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it, I write no vntruth, nor no more then I haue ſeene, and know to be true: and to make ſome proofe thereof, Maſter <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Spencer</hi> of <hi>Clardon</hi> in Warwickeſhire, a man knowne to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſhewed me about Bartholomewtide, in the yeare of our Lord, one thouſand ſix hundred and twelue, being the drieſt ſpring that yeare that was of many yeares before, or ſince, many hundreds of ſallow or willow ſetts, that hee had cauſed to bee ſet the ſame yeare, which ſets are not aboue a foote long aboue ground, ſet in bare, drie, grauelly, hungry ground; notwithſtanding the drie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the yeare, there were very few that tooke not; and the reſt had ſo taken roote, as they put forth at the rootes, by the moiſtneſſe of the deaws, but not at the toppes: and he himſelfe told mee in Candlemaſſe Terme, one thouſand ſixe hundred and thirteene, when this Booke was in Printing, that they tooke at the ground, and proſpered well: hee further told me, that of his owne knowledge, the ſeed of willow would grow. And it hath beene reported to me by men of good worth, that the chippes of willow wil grow; which I doe the better beleeue; for I haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſeene the chippes of poplar, aſpe, and awbell grow, ſo as they would not be deſtroyed but by plucking them vp by the rootes; for of all wood, cattell will leaſt browſe of thoſe woods. And further, that willow and ſallow will grow on any ground, hauing two foote ſoile, it is to be ſeene by as many as will obſerue it, that in all chalkie, flinty, ſandy, or any other drie ground, they will grow from hedge-ſtakes. And I haue ſeene, and it is to be ſeene, as great ſallow and willow trees come of ſtakes, as may be ſeene in any lowe grounds, both ſounder and longer laſting by many degrees, for all will put forth ſo neare the ground, as I do write, and in woods on the drieſt ground that is; there is no wood com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to thoſe woods in growth, but Aſh: for chips of Elme, I haue ſeene many trees of them. And for the better proofe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ſir <hi>Thomas Treſham</hi> of <hi>Newton</hi> in Northamptonſhire ſhewed mee the laſt Summer, at the leaſt a dozen trees, that of his owne knowledge came of chips. And about Michaelmaſſe laſt, it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Earle of <hi>Kent</hi> to inuite mee to dine with him in <hi>Bedford,</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:183843:19"/> where there was at leaſt ſeuen or eight Knights and Eſquires at the Table, ſome of which doubted of the growing of the chips of Elme; whereunto maiſter <hi>Lee</hi> a Iuſtice of Peace, dwelling with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in halfe a mile of <hi>Bedford</hi> affirmed, ſaying, they would grow; for he cauſed an Elme to be felld at the Spring of the yeare, and to be carried to his houſe, into a yard where no cattell came, and where the Elme was ſquared, and the chippes cleane raked off: notwithſtanding, many of the ſmalleſt that remained, ſprung vp as thicke as hemp-ſeed on a land: and other proofs I could make, if occaſion ſerued: as for the rootes or boughes, I haue heard no doubt made of them, neyther can any make doubt of the grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the maſte or ſeedes of any other wood. And for any wood to grow ſo thicke, it is leſſe to be doubted, for in Cambridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, where moſt ſprings of Elme are, it is to be ſeene, that after the vnderlings be cut away, they grow as thicke as I write of, where they are left ſo thicke, as for Aſh or any other ſeedes of wood, it will (for ſo few or more yeares) grow ſo thicke: And I haue ſeene many Groues of Aſh that haue beene ſet, that after many yeares haue taken holde, and growne ſo thicke. The laſt Summer, about Michaelmaſſe, it pleaſed ſir <hi>Walter Montague</hi> to ſhew me a Groue by his houſe, within fiue miles of <hi>Northampton,</hi> which he had cauſed to be ſet not much thinner; in which Groue he had cauſed ſome to be felled that liked not, which forth of the rootes of ſuch as were felled, there were yong Aſhes ſprung vp, of a yard and three quarters high, of one yeares growth. And I haue ſeene the like in many places: the onely way to make yong trees after they are remoued, to grow more in one yeare, then after they are moued, in three, is to fell them by the ground, after two yeares, when they haue taken roote. If any ſhall aske why wood doth not proue ſo well by many degrees: In all ſprings of wood, I anſwere, there are two reaſons at the leaſt why it doth not, the one is, no wood groweth ſo ſpeedily, by the halfe, as theſe woods; but the ſpeciall reaſon is the Springs, are not ordered, they are fuller of haſell, maple-buſhes, and other wood that ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to ſmall proofe, and ſo thicke of vnderlings, as the other can not generally proſper, but ſome few that get vp and choake all the reſt. Neither is the ſixt part of any ſprings that I ſee furniſhed with ſuch proouing wood. And for further proofe for timber,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:183843:19"/> one maſter <hi>Skipwith</hi> in Norffolke, within three miles of <hi>Downane</hi> ſhewed mee a Groue, planted by his father, of foure and thirtie yeares growth, of Oakes and Aſhe, growne ſo tall, as Herons haue bred in them theſe three yeares paſt: which trees grow not aboue two yards one from another, ſome planted by akornes, and Aſhe-keyes, and ſome by yong ſets, cut and vſed as quicke: ſome difference there is of their growth, the ſetts are the taller, but little the bigger. All theſe kindes of planting, by common reaſon and experience cannot be denied, nor the profite there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: by reaſon thereof it may appeare, that whereas there is contained in this kingdome fiue and twentie millions of Acres whereupon wood will grow and proſper, ouer and aboue the waſte whereon wood will not prooue, if it were planted, as on ſtony hilles, great mooriſh, linggy moores and moſſes, waters and watery mooriſh fennes and high-wayes: forth of which fiue and twenty millions take but one hundred thouſand acres, and diuide it into tenne thouſand parts, it will yeelde to euerie pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in this Kingdome, if there were tenne thouſand (as there is not) two thouſand fiue hundred acres; take foorth of the two thouſand fiue hundred, but one hundred and tenne Acres, and plant tenne Acres thereof in rowes, as before is directed, and there may be raiſed in tenne Acres of the hundred and ten, foure and twenty thouſand two hundred trees for timber, two yards betweene euery one of them one way, and ten the other, to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh euery pariſh, and the ground thereby much improued, and within thirty yeares the fences of all grounds, being made, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, will yeeld ſuch ſtore of fire-wood, as there will be no neede of the aforeſaid plantation, for firewood, or any other ſprings, but all may be ſtocked vp and conuerted to tillage and paſture. For the better effecting of this buſineſſe, it is thought conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, that an Act might paſſe, that it may be lawfull for all men to incloſe, ground for this plantation in common fields, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny townes may be furniſhed by their commons.</p>
               <p>So as if coales ſhould decay neare the coaſts (as they doe too faſt in many places within the Land) which as yet is no more feared, then the want of wood was generally feared through the whole Kingdome, ſpecially in <hi>London, Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Oxford,</hi> forty yeares agoe, when the poreſt ſort ſcorned to eate a peece of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:183843:20"/> meate roaſted with ſea-coles, which now the beſt Magiſtrates are conſtrained to doe. If a man in that time ſhould haue fore-told this want of wood, that now the whole Kingdome is come to, it would haue been holden a thing vnpoſſible, the plenty of wood was then ſo great, and ſo good means to continue the ſame: with much more reaſon may it now bee feared, that in the like time coles may be more decayed, conſidering the aboundance that is ſpent of them, not onely in this Realme, but in other Nations, and no meanes to increaſe them: for by experience it is general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowne, that after they be once got, they neuer more grow or increaſe.</p>
               <p>And briefly to ſhew the premiſſes, firſt, that one thouſand two hundred and ten trees may be planted for timber in one acre, and euery tree to haue foure yards of ground to grow on, it is not to be doubted, for there is to be ſeene in euery county ſome groues that haue beene planted by the plough, and ſome by hand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in three ſcore yeares, that grow as thicke both of Oake and Aſh, and naturally groues of Elme and Wich trees.</p>
               <p>And that timber trees will grow and thriue well in rowes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two yards aſunder one way, and tenne the other, it is alſo to be ſeene in euery county about many cloſes, and on all ſoiles, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Oake, Aſh, Beech, or Elme that do grow, ſpecially in towns, by the high-wayes ſides, trees that are a hundred or two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares old, planted or preſerued, when wood was not of the worth that it is in this inſtant, which in this age is thought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be ſo raiſed: nay, which is more ſtrange, as great huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands as we thinke our ſelues, it is apparent in euery towne, men chooſe rather to make dead hedges euery yeare, then to plant, as they may doe by wood, and make a fence for hundreds of yeares, as may appeare by the wood already growing in ſuch fences, which will yeelde yearely profite, and preuent the great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints that are daily made of the poore for the breaking of hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And that all fences may be made of trees onely, it is euident, eſpecially about woods, where in the hedges there is want of thornes, they plaſh wood, which hath laine, in common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as it doth appeare by the greatneſſe of the trees, at the leaſt, a hundred yeares, and growne ſo cloſe as no man can ſee between the trees, being plaſhed, and for the moſt part, laid ſo lowe as
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:183843:20"/> beaſts browſe off the tops, much more will they laſt many more yeares, being laid, and not cut at the rootes to receiue water, the toppes being laid ſo high as cattell cannot reach them, or being vnlayed, may grow vpright, to ſtand as pales, which may be lopped for fire-wood, and browſe for Deere or Cattell. Thus much for fences of Parkes and other incloſed grounds, and that this kinde of fire-wood may be planted ſo thicke and prooue ſo well, it may appeare in all coppies, or ſprings of wood, that on Aſh or Sallow rootes they grow thicker then I proportion; and all men know that willow and ſallow is inferiour to no wood in growth, eſpecially being planted ſo neare the ground. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why all ſpring woods make not ſuch proofe, is, that ſome ſprings ſtand, for the moſt part, of beech, ſome with oake, ſome with hornebeane, and many with maple, haſell and thornes, all which are no proouing wood for fire. I neuer met with any but they approoue, that Aſh, Sallow, or Willow, doth grow more in one yeare, then any of the aforeſaid woods will grow in two: and Elme and Wich is not much inferiour to the Aſh in growth; ſo it is apparent, that if all men would furniſh their ſprings with thoſe kinds of wood, and cut away all the vnderlings at 3 yeres growth, when the wood will be worth the labor, no man would ſtocke or grub vp woods, as they doe, except it were into rowes; and that all thoſe kindes of woods will grow and proſper being preſerued and maintained, no man will make doubt, in regard that both reaſon &amp; experience makes proofe thereof, and where thoſe kinds of wood grow not ſo thicke; approuedly ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing plaſhed from the rootes of them that grow, being ſhread, and a little of the tops cut off, and laide three fingers deepe in tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and couered with earth, will grow and proſper. And that euery buſh will breede a tree (the meanes being ſet rather of a yong plant that may be raiſed by nurſeries, then by the other meanes before ſet downe, in regard that I finde all kinde of maſte ſubiect to mice and other vermine. It is apparent in all forreſts, chaſes, parkes, and commons, incloſed grounds, hedges and high-wayes ſides, by the buſhes that grow about many trees, both old and yoong; and many there be that confeſſe all this to be true by experience, that little obſerue their owne experience. Thus by his Maieſties fauor and bounty, together with the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:183843:21"/> and good inſtructions that I receiued from the worthie Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths men: I holde my ſelfe bound in conſcience, not onely to ſeeke all experience that may tend to this buſineſſe, but likewiſe to put all men in minde thereof, to the end that if Sea-coles ſhall decay, good take-heede come not too late.</p>
               <p>The Premiſſes conſidered, it is generally hoped, that ſome good courſe will be taken, to preuent ſo great an inconuenience. Thus with an honeſt intention, for the publique good of this kingdome, the content of his Maieſtie, and all good men, I conclude, leauing the ſucceſſe to GOD, who is the director of mens harts to all good offices.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
